Wollaston, Quincy, Mass. Wollaston Congregational Church records, 1874-1968.
Congregational Library & Archives
Wollaston, Quincy, Mass. Wollaston Congregational Church records, 1874-1968.
RG1048
Congregational Library & Archives
1.44 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
On September 23, 1874, a meeting was called for the organization of a Congregational church in Wollaston, Quincy, Massachusetts. The resulting Wollaston Congregational Society met in local churches and member residences until the completion of the first meeting house, which was erected in 1875 and dedicated in 1876. Wollaston Congregational Church was officially incorporated on November 15, 1898. Construction on a replacement for the first meeting house ended with a dedication on March 28 1926. Wollaston Congregational Church voted to join the United Church of Christ on January 29, 1960 and is still active today. This collection contains the earliest records of Wollaston Congregational Church and its auxiliary groups and includes financial records, membership lists, meeting minutes, reports, and correspondence. A church history, produced as a scrapbook in 1951, documents the first 75 years of the church.
Wollaston Congregational Church (Wollaston, Quincy, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by Wollaston Congregational Church (Wollaston, Quincy, Mass.) in February 1962.
Biographical / Historical
The land that is modern Quincy, Massachusetts is the historic seat of the Neponset Band of the Massachusett Tribe's leader Sac'hem Chickataubut and the seasonal, ancestral home of the Massachusett, Wampanoag, and Pokanoket tribes. The descendants of the Neponset Band of the Massachusett Tribe, the Ponkapoag people, inhabited the future site of the town before and during the first recording of the colonization of the area on September 30, 1621 under Captain Myles Standish of the Plymouth Colony. Quincy's present-day neighborhood of Wollaston paralleled colonial expansion in the area and developed as a European settlement after Thomas Morton, Captain Richard Wollaston, and a group of colonists parted with the Plymouth Colony as early as 1624.
On September 23, 1874, a meeting was called for the organization of a Congregational church in Wollaston, Quincy, Massachusetts. The resulting Wollaston Congregational Society met in local churches and member residences until the completion of the first meeting house, which was erected in 1875 and dedicated in 1876. Reverend Francis N. Zabriskee, D.D., acted as first regular pastor. The church was constructed on the corner lot between Lincoln Avenue and Winthrop Avenue in Quincy, Massachusetts in the neighborhood then known as Wollaston Heights. Specifications for the wooden Gothic Revival were made by architect Samuel D. Kelly of Boston with J.D. Rollins and D. R. Edgerton of Edgarton & Rollins contracted to complete the building on or before January 1, 1876. Wollaston Congregational Church was incorporated on November 15, 1898, effectively dissolving the Wollaston Congregational Society.
The Wollaston Congregational Church an acquired additional, neighboring property in 1900. A new parish house was built and dedicated on November 14, 1915. Discussions regarding the potential of a new meeting house arose in 1923 to accommodate increased membership. The eventual construction of a new meeting house began in 1925. The corner stone was laid on June 14 of the same year, and the building was dedicated on March 28, 1926.
The Wollaston Congregational Church maintained several auxiliary groups throughout its history. A meeting was held on February 17, 1875 for the organization Ladies Benevolent Society. The society outlined its constitution and bylaws on February 26, 1875. The Auxiliary to the Women's Board of Missions was organized in 1887 and merged with the Ladies Benevolent Society in May 1918 to form the Women's Union. Also included is the Congregational Men's Club, which was started in 1906 and renamed the Chester I. Campbell Men's Club in 1933.
Wollaston Congregational Church voted to join the United Church of Christ on January 29, 1960 and is still active today.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the records, correspondence, and programs related to the gathering and construction of Wollaston Congregational Church of Quincy, Massachusetts since its initial organization in 1874. Included within the records are the administrative and society meeting minutes and reports, financial records, and membership lists of the church. The records also document the formation and mission of the church's auxiliary groups such as the Ladies Benevolent Society, Wollaston Auxiliary, and Woman's Union through meeting minutes and personal correspondence. A scrapbook on the history of the first 75 years of the church, which includes photographs from the early twentieth century and a drawing from memory of the original meeting house, further contextualizes the materials.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Records in each series and subseries have been primarily arranged chronologically by start date, and secondarily by topic.
Bibliography
Edwards, William Churchill. Historic Quincy, Massachusetts. 1st ed. Quincy: City of Quincy, 1957.
Native Land Digital. Native Land Digital, October 8, 2021. https://native-land.ca/.
"We Are the Descendants." The Massachusett Tribe at Ponkapoag. The Massachusett Tribe at Ponkapoag, 2023. https://massachusetttribe.org/.
Church records and registers.; Church charities.; Church correspondence.; Church records and registers.; Church buildings.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church societies.; Letters.; Photographs.; Women in charitable work.; Wollaston (Quincy, Mass.) -- Church history.; Wollaston Congregational Church (Wollaston, Quincy, Mass.)
- Church administration, 1874 1951; 1874-1951; 17 Files; (13 volumes, 4 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains church records such as printed by-laws, administrative reports, meeting minutes, and account books. Included in these records are copies of church governance, descriptions of committee activities, specifications for the construction of the first meeting house, and vital statistics such as membership lists. A scrapbook reviewing the history of the church from 1876 to 1951 further contextualizes the materials.
  - Church and society records, 1874 1898; 1874-1898 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Society records, 1874 1925; 1874-1925 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Separated Materials
    Materials removed from this volume are stored separately in folder titled "Various transactions, programs, and correspondence, 1890-1950".
  - Church records, 1874 1876; 1874-1876 (Box 1, Volume 19)
  - "A Review of its First 75 Years 1876 – 1951" (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Various transactions, programs, and correspondence, 1890 1950; 1890-1950 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    This file is comprised of materials removed from the volume titled "Society records, 1874-1925".
  - Church records, 1898 1899; 1898-1899 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Executive committee records, 1899 1915; 1899-1915 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - Prudential committee reports, 1888 1898; 1888-1898 (Box 1, Volume 7)
  - Prudential committee meeting minutes, 1899 1930; 1899-1930 (Box 1, Volume 8)
  - Prudential committee meeting minutes, 1930 1939; 1930-1939 (Box 1, Volume 9)
  - Account book, 1927 1943; 1927-1943 (Box 1, Volume 10)
    Materials removed from this volume are stored separately in folder titled "Wollaston Congregational fire insurance and accounting note, 1935". The accounting note was discovered on page 179 of the volume.
  - Executive committee and committee of twenty five meeting minutes, 1932 1939; 1932-1939 (Box 1, Volume 5)
    Materials removed from this volume are stored separately in file titled "Debt of Honor Campaign program, 1938". The materials were found with the volume entry for February 27, 1938.
  - Wollaston Congregational fire insurance and accounting note, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    This file is comprised of materials removed the volume titled "Account book, 1927-1943". The accounting note was discovered on page 179 of the volume.
  - Wollaston Congregational Church Forward Movement Fund cash book, 1936 1943; 1936-1943 (Box 1, Volume 11)
  - Church by-laws, 1936 (Box 1, Volume 6)
  - Debt of Honor Campaign program, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    This file is comprised of a pamphlet removed the volume titled "Exeuctive committee and committee of twenty five meeting minutes, 1932-1939". The material was found with the volume entry for February 27, 1938.
  - Dr. Isaiah W. Sneath Memorial Fund account book, 1940 1941; 1940-1941 (Box 1, Volume 12)
- Auxiliary groups, 1875 1968; 1875-1968; 13 Files; (7 volumes, 6 folders)
  This series contains the records of Wollaston Congregational Church's auxiliary groups. Included are the meeting minutes, financial information, and personal and organizational correspondence of the Ladies Benevolent Society, Auxiliary W.B.M., Women's Missionary Association, and Woman's Union.
  - Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1875 1892; 1875-1892 (Box 1, Volume 13)
    Materials removed from this volume are stored separately in folder titled "History of Woman's Union & Benevolent Society correspondence, 1901-1968". Letter from the Calhoun Colored School was discovered on page 92 of volume.
  - Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1900 1915; 1900-1915 (Box 1, Volume 14)
    Materials removed from this volume are stored separately in folder titled "Correspondence and Woman's Home Missionary Association records, 1911".
  - History of Woman's Union & Benevolent Society and correspondence, 1901 1968; 1901-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    This file is comprised of materials removed the volume titled "Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1875-1892". Letter from the Calhoun Colored School was discovered on page 92 of volume.
  - Correspondence and Women's Home Missionary Association records, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    This file is comprised of materials removed from the volume titled "Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1900-1915".
  - Wollaston Auxiliary W.B.M. records, 1912 1918; 1912-1918 (Box 1, Volume 16)
  - Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1916 1918; 1916-1918 (Box 1, Volume 15)
    Materials removed from this volume are stored separately in folder titled "Letters to Ladies Benevolent Society, 1918".
  - Woman's Union meeting minutes, 1918 1921; 1918-1921 (Box 1, Volume 17)
    This file is comprised of a brochure removed the volume titled "Woman's Union meeting minutes, 1918-1921". The item was disovered on page 13 of the volume.
  - Letters to Ladies Benevolent Society, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    This file is comprised of materials removed the volume titled "Ladies Benevolent Society records, 1916-1918".
  - Norfolk and Pilgrim Branch W.B.M. Report, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Woman's Union records, 1921 1926; 1921-1926 (Box 1, Volume 18)
    Materials removed from this volume are stored separately in folder titled "Correspondence, Report of Serving Committee, and Ladies' Night Ticket, 1922-1923, undated". Clipping titled "Our Slogan" and Ladies' Night ticket was discovered on page 184 of volume. Letter from Dorothy H. Taylor on Boston University Women Graduates' Club letterhead was discovered on page 238 of volume.
  - Correspondence, Report of Serving Committee, and Ladies' Night Ticket, 1922 1923; 1922-1923, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    This file is comprised of materials removed the volume titled "Woman's Union records, 1921-1926". Clipping titled "Our Slogan" and Ladies' Night ticket was discovered on page 184 of volume. Letter from Dorothy H. Taylor on Boston University Women Graduates' Club letterhead was discovered on page 238 of volume.
  - Secretary Records of the Woman's Unions, 1926 1935; 1926-1935 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    Materials removed from this volume are stored separately in folder titled "Receipts and letters, 1932, undated". Receipts was discovered on page 129 of volume. Letter from Chaplain William S. Kelley was discovered on page 211 of volume.
  - Receipts and letters, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    This file is comprised of materials removed the volume titled "Secretary Records of the Woman's Unions, 1926-1935". Receipts was discovered on page 129 of volume. Letter from Chaplain William S. Kelley was discovered on page 211 of volume.